Vitamin B12 supplementation is crucial
for anyone eating a plant-based diet,
but does it have any side effects?
Watch the video to find out.
"Do Vitamin B12 Supplements Cause
Acne, Bone Fractures, and Lung Cancer?"
Acne is a disease unique to humans.
Why do humans get acne?
Well, think about the distribution of those greasy
sebaceous glands—face, chest and back—
exactly the same structures
that pose the greatest
obstruction during childbirth.
So hey, maybe having a little
extra lubrication at those sites
would help make the baby
more slippery for birth,
conferring a selective advantage
for successful delivery.
OK, but what triggers them
to become inflamed into zits later on?
While in westernized societies, acne
is a nearly universal skin disease
afflicting up to 95% of teens,
in some populations eating
more traditional diets not even
single cases could be found.
This suggests that perhaps
nutrition counseling should be
a first-line therapy for individuals
with mild to moderate acne.
It looks like it's the high glycemic
foods and dairy products.
So we're talking sugar, soda,
refined junky carbs, white flour,
breakfast cereal, and dairy products
like milk, cheese, yogurt, whey,
as well as saturated and trans fats
concentrated in meat,
dairy, junk, and fast food.
So for example, acne patients should
be encouraged to discontinue
any whey protein supplements
they might be taking.
The relationship between milk and
acne severity may be explained
by the presence in dairy of normal
reproductive sex steroid hormones
or the enhanced production of
growth hormones such as IGF-1.
And if you re like, "Wait, I gave up
dairy a month ago and still no change,"
It should be noted that changes
in acne due to any dietary changes
are likely to take at least 10 to 12
weeks, so you have to stick to it.
Not surprisingly, acne patients
were more than twice as likely
to have a non-vegan diet
compared to controls,
but the difference did not
reach statistical significance.
So maybe the vegans were
eating a lot of vegan junk?
But what about this:
"Vitamin B12 Induced Acnes"
Our fellow great ape herbivores like
gorillas get all the B12 they need
practicing the eating of feces,
but my preference would be
to take B12 supplements.
And you don't have to worry
about getting too much because
there are evidently no reports
of adverse effects associated
with excess B12 intake,
but that's not true.
First described back in the 1950's,
about 1 in 10 people erupt in acne
within days or even just within hours
of getting an injection of vitamin B12,
which then disappears rapidly
when you stop injecting them.
At the time, we had no idea
what the mechanism might be,
a problem still unsolved even
up until just to a few years ago.
But then we finally figured it out:
Vitamin B12 modulates
the gene expression of the skin
bacteria that cause acne.
They swabbed the skin of 10 people
before and after being injected
with Vitamin B12. It turns out
the level of B12 on your skin
is proportional to the level in
your blood, and so after injection
the bacteria on your skin have
to make less of their own B12,
and so the acne bacteria could
concentrate instead on using
its cellular machinery to churn out
more compounds to attack your face.
Without excess B12 on the skin,
shown here in green,
the bacteria has to make most on
its own at the expense of porphyrins,
which can trigger acne inflammation.
When there's lots of B12 floating around,
the bacteria can not waste resources
and focus instead on trying to pimple
you up. OK, so wait, what do you do?
Those on plant-based diets have
to take supplemental B12. Yes,
but we don't have to get injections.
Vitamin B12-related acne tends to
occur only in dosages in excess of
5,000 to 10,000 micrograms a week,
well in excess of the 50 micrograms
a day I recommend, or
alternately my 2,000
single weekly dose. I mean
the only time you'd be taking
between 5,000 to 10,000 a week
is if you were treating B12 deficiency.
If you remember from my previous
video, B12 deficiency is treated with
1,000 micrograms a day
for a month or more,
and that could potentially trigger it,
as noted in this vegan woman
who wasn't taking B12,
developed B12 deficiency,
and had to be treated with such high
doses her face erupted in acne.
So all the more reason not to fall
B12 deficient in the first place.
But look, if worse comes to worst,
even if you do get B12 injections,
the likelihood of it triggering
acne may only be about 1 in 10.
In 2019, a study found an
“Association Between
High Intakes of Vitamins B6 and B12
From Food and Supplements With
(the) Risk of Hip Fracture Among
Postmenopausal Women
in the Harvard Nurses’ Health Study.”
But note, it was only
the combined high intake
of vitamins B6 and B12.
We know that treatment with
high doses of vitamin B6
may alone increase hip fracture risk.
After a decade or so,
those who had been taking
high dose B6 supplements had about
a 40% higher hip fracture risk,
but not in those taking B12.
And that’s what the
Harvard study found too—
high intake of vitamin B12 alone
was not associated with increased risk.
In fact, some observational
studies suggest slightly
lower fracture risk at
high B12 blood levels.
But what we care about most
are interventional studies,
where people are randomized to
B12 so we can see what happens.
And when you do that,
no increased fracture risk
among those given B12.
In conclusion, based on
randomized controlled trials,
high doses of vitamin
B12 have not been shown
to be associated with
the risk of fractures.
OK, but what about this?
In 2017, a study found that men
taking vitamin B12 supplements
appeared to have an increase
in lung cancer risk.
Now, they didn’t find any
such association in women,
and it was mostly among smoking men.
Could it be that B12 was like
feeding some budding tumors?
I mean, it’s hard to imagine
a vitamin being carcinogenic
on its own, and especially somehow
only in men but not women.
The bottom line is that
replication of these ﬁndings
with additional studies is necessary,
and indeed when you put all the
observational studies together,
there was no signiﬁcant correlation
between the levels of B12
in the blood and lung cancer,
whether you smoked or not.
If anything, most studies
seemed to be trending
towards higher B12 levels
being protective.
But then, in 2018, a new study
found an association
between overall lung cancer
risk and higher
circulating levels of B12,
again appearing to be
more of a smoker thing.
Now, this was another
observational study.
Those with higher B12
levels were just observed
to have higher cancer levels;
and so, those of you who have been
following my work know the drill.
There are two potential issues that arise
in observational studies that
prevent you from ascribing
cause-and-effect: confounding
factors, also known as
“lurking variables” and
reverse causation.
What might be a lurking variable
in this case, a third factor
associated with both higher
B12 levels and cancer,
that may be the true cause?
Well, who has higher levels of B12
circulating in their blood?
Those who eat lots of meat and dairy,
in fact probably the most
important contributors.
And those who eat more meat do
tend to have more lung cancer,
about 35% more risk for every
about daily quarter-pound burger,
and 20% increased risk for each
like, breakfast sausage link.
So, no wonder those with higher
B12 levels in their blood
could have more lung cancer.
The B12 could just be a
marker for meat intake.
And, if you remember,
reverse causation is when
instead of X leading to Y,
maybe Y is instead leading to X.
So, instead of high B12 blood
levels leading to cancer,
maybe cancer leads to high blood levels.
And indeed, nearly three-quarters
of cancer patients
exhibit elevated B12 levels.
So, elevated B12 levels may
just be a marker for cancer.
There are all sorts of things
beyond just taking extra B12
that can raise your levels:
liver problems, kidney problems,
bone marrow problems, and cancer.
So, high levels may just
be a marker of a brewing,
not-yet-diagnosed, cancer.
Yeah, but what about
observational studies
specifically linking supplement
use to lung cancer?
That too could be reverse causation,
where being at risk for
cancer—in other words,
being a smoker—makes you
more likely to take vitamins
to try to decrease your risk.
Basically, any behavior tied to
smoking could be indirectly tied
to lung cancer, but it’s
the smoking itself, of course,
that’s the real lung cancer risk.
So, we’re left with this chicken
or the egg causality dilemma,
which is why ideally, we need
randomized controlled trials
to see if there’s any cause-and-effect.
This became even more urgent
with genetic evidence
suggesting that those just
born with higher lifelong levels
may be at increased risk.
Thankfully we do have
randomized controlled trials—
over a dozen randomized
controlled trials
randomizing thousands of people
up to 2,000 micrograms of B12
every single day for years and…
vitamin B supplementation does not
have any effect on getting cancer,
dying from cancer, or dying overall,
and this includes specifically
looking at lung cancer.
In fact, if anything, vitamin B
supplements may actually lower
the risk of the most
dangerous form of skin cancer.